We sigh whenever we're about to come to a standstill
終わりなき旅の途中　立ち止まりそうな時
Owarinaki tabi no tochuu tachidomarisouna toki
While moving on this endless journey.
深いため息こぼす　僕らは
Fukai tameiki kobosu bokura wa
Everytime we lunge for it, it escapes and flies off.
掴みかけてはまた離れていった
Tsukamikaketewa mata hanareteitta
But now, there's nothing to be afraid of
でも今はもう何も恐れることはない
Demo ima wa mou nanimo osoreru koto wa nai
The powerful ties that bind our hearts
心を繋ぐ強い絆は
Kokoro wo tsunagu tsuyoi kizuna wa
Will never come loose.
けして解けはしないさ
Keshite hodoke wa shinai sa
After a lifetime of searching, we finally arrived
探し続けて辿り着いた
Sagashitsuzukete tadoritsuita
Here, where the period lies.
この場所で Period に
Kono basho de piriodo ni
Let's change all our sorrow and rage to power.
悲しみ怒り 力に変えて
Kanashimi ikari chikara ni kaete
Destiny is right within our reach.
運命はすぐそばに
Unmei wa sugu soba ni
On the day before the Promised Day,
約束の日を翌日に控え
Alphonse Elric lies dormant in the Eastern training grounds.
東部演習場に潜む
アルフォンス·エルリック
However, he is captured by the sudden appearances of the Homunculi, Gluttony and Pride.
だが  現れた人造人間
グラトニーとプライドに
捕らえられてしまうのだった
Alphonse...
アルフォンス
Pick yourself up...
しっかりしなさい  アルフォンス
Alphonse...
Who...
誰
It's far too early for you to die.
逝くのはまだ早いよ
I still have plenty of things for you to do.
まだまだ  君は…
利用させてもらわなきゃならない
Excuse me...
すみません  ここ  カナマですか
Are we in Kanama?
Mr. Hoh!
ホーさん
You've got some visitors.
客だよ
So you're here, Edwa-
来たか  エドワー…
God, that felt good.
すっきりした
The first thing you do is punch me in the face?!
いきなり殴るなんて
ひどいじゃないか
And with your right hand, too!
しかも  右で
Looks like you made some new friends.
お友達が増えたな
お友…
Fri-
成り行きで
We're just working with him due to the circumstances.
行動を共にしているだけだ
And I'm the boss of all of them.
ちなみにオレはこいつら全員のボスな
Oh my.
それはそれは
Thank you for taking care of my son.
息子がお世話になっております
いやいや  本当にクソ生意気な息子さんで
Not a problem.
Though he's one hell of a brat.
うっせぇ
Shut up!
Interesting tattoo you've got there.
変わった入れ墨だね
Oh.
This.
これね
Guess there's no point in hiding it.
隠してもしゃあないか
You'd better not hide anything either, old man.
おっさんも隠さず話せよ
Tomorrow is the "Promised Day", right?
明日が約束の日なんだろ
Yeah.
I'll tell you guys everything.
すべて話すよ
Guess you won't be able to accept it as easily as Alphonse did.
やはりアルフォンスほどには
素直に受け入れられないか
You told Al too?!
アルにも話したのか
Yeah.
He probably has a lot to think about, but he accepted it.
いろいろ思うところあるだろうが
受け入れてくれたよ
The philosopher's stone you've been looking for is right here.
お前が欲しがっていた賢者の石だ
Do you want to use it?
使うか
Don't fuck with me!
ふざけんな
They're lives of people who are totally uninvolved!
関係ない人たちの命だぞ
We lost our bodies due to our own carelessness!
自分のせいで
体をなくしたオレたちが
使っていいわけねぇだろ
What gives us the right to use their lives?!
I'm glad my son grew up to say that.
そう言える息子でよかった
A solar eclipse occurs tomorrow.
明日  日食が起きる
He's planning on using that.
あいつはそれを利用する気だ
A solar eclipse?
日食を…利用する
How would he use that?
Edward.
エドワード
Would you be willing to help me stop his plans?
あいつの野望を阻止するのを
手伝ってくれるか
'Help'?!
手伝う
Don't get the wrong idea!
勘違いするな
てめぇなんぞと組まなくたって
I'm going to beat the hell out of that geezer even if I don't  have to work with you!
オレはあのヒゲ野郎をぶっとばす
I'm just listening to what you have to say right now because teaming up with you might increase our odds of 	winning!
ただ今は  手ぇ組んだ方が
確実に勝てそうだから
話を聞いてやってるだけだ
I'm glad to hear...
よかった
Whatever the reason may be, you're willing to fight alongside me.
理由がなんであれ
一緒に戦ってくれるんだな
Granny Pinako asked me to tell you Mom's last words.
ピナコばっちゃんから
母さんの遺言を頼まれた
"Sorry I couldn't keep my promise."
「約束守れなくて  ごめん
"I'm going to have to leave you first."
先に逝く」って
Message delivered!
確かに伝えた…
Hey, shouldn't you try to sit knee to knee with your father and open up to him?
お前よ
もうちょっとおやっさんと
ひざを交えて話した方が
いいんじゃねぇか
そうそう
Yeah, man.
せめておやじって呼んでやれよ
You should at least call him "Old Man".
Seems like a lot happened in the past,
過去にいろいろあったようだが
but he definitely doesn't seem like someone who would abandon his wife.
ありゃあ  カミさんを
捨てるような男じゃないな
He probably has a lot of personal reasons.
きっと  いろいろあんだよ
Come on. Listen to what he has to say.
なっ  ちゃんと話を聞いてやれ
Shut up already!
だあ  もううっせぇな
オレだって  いろいろあんだよ
I've got a lot of personal reasons, too!
いろいろって  なんだ
For example?
You're probably just too stubborn and proud.
どうせ  つまらん意地だろ
You can't organize your thoughts very well, right?
気持ちの整理がつかねぇんだろ
Can't really blame you.
無理もねぇ
生きた人間の形をした賢者の石
He's a philosopher's stone in the shape of a human.
To top it off, he's also your dad.
しかも  それが
てめぇの父親だってんだからなぁ
That's not all of it.
それだけじゃねぇよ
He just showed a side of himself that I wasn't really expecting.
あいつがちょっと意外だったから…
You know... someday, I'll turn into a wrinkled old woman who looks like a monster.
私だって  いつか
しわくちゃのおばあさんになるわよ
But no matter how I end up looking, I'll always be happy to take a picture with the family where everyone is 	smiling.
でもね  どんな姿になっても
みんなで一緒に笑っていたいの
So please... stay with your family.
だから  ずっと家族でいて
Trisha, I'm going.
トリシャ  オレ行くよ
Please wait for me.
待っててくれ
Okay.
はい
I'll be waiting.
待っています
"Sorry I couldn't keep my promise."
「約束守れなくて  ごめん
"I'm going to have to leave you first.", huh...
先に逝ってる」か…
Even though we couldn't age and die together,
一緒に老いて死ぬのはかなわなかったが
you must believe from the bottom of your heart that I'll come after you in the future.
あとから  必ずオレが来ると
信じてくれてるんだな
It'll be tomorrow... Trisha.
明日だ トリシャ
Here you go.
はい  どうぞ
Thanks.
ありがとう
What are you going to do with that?
なにすんだ  そんなもん
You're going to wear something flashy like this again?
またこんな派手なの着る気か
なんで  赤なんだ
Why's it gotta be red?
This is probably going to be our last battle against them.
たぶん  ヤツらと
最後の戦いになるだろうからよ
I'm going to need to be psyched.
気合い入れていかねぇとな
Hey, you know...
あのさ  何も
You don't really have to stick with me through all of this.
オレにつきあうことないんだぜ
I personally think it would be better for you guys if you were to leave to attend to your own business from 		here.
ここで別れといた方が
おっさんたちのためだと思うんだけど
Hey, you're one of my henchmen. Don't go ordering me around.
手下のくせに勝手に決めんなよ
I guess you guys want to return to your original bodies too?
やっぱ  あれ
元の体に戻りたいとか
I wonder...
どうかな
この体  いろいろ便利だし
This body can be pretty convenient.
I guess I wouldn't mind staying like this forever.
別にこのままでもかまわないかな
That's the spirit!
そうでなくちゃ
Then... why?
じゃあ  なんで
まあ  あれだ
Well, you know.
We don't really have anywhere else to go.
ほかに行く所もないし
My animal instincts tell me that I'm better off staying here.
ここにいる方がいい目見られるってな
野生の勘がいってる
Okay...
And what about you?
お前はなんでよ
Weren't you saying something about running away from the other Homunculi?
人造人間のヤツらから
とんずらこくとか言ってなかったか
You're asking why I came back to Central?
なんでセントラルに戻ってきたかって
Not tellin'.
教えねぇよ
What is it?
なんだよ
Al!
アル
Man, don't scare me like that!
なんだ  脅かすなよ
I'm glad we were able to join up!
合流できてよかった
元気だったか
How have you been?
Looks like you were safe and sound too, Brother.
兄さんも無事だったんだね
Huh? Aren't you supposed to be with Major Miles?
あれっ
お前  マイルズ少佐のところに
いたんじゃないのか
Is everything going well over there?
あっちは大丈夫なのかよ
I actually wanted to talk to you about that.
そのことで話が  ちょっと来て
Could you come here for a second?
Y-Yeah.
Al... is something wrong?
アル  お前どこか悪いのか
Why do you ask?
どうして
I dunno... I just got a feeling.
いや  なんとなく…
Ed!
エド
Lin!
リン
そいつから離れろ
Get away from him!
He's...
そいつは…
That's...!
それは…
W-What's going on?!
なっ  なんだぁ
So you joined them, Greed.
そちらに付いたのですか
グリード
And you were taken control of by a human like that...
また  そんな人間に
乗っ取られるなんて…
Your soul is too weak!
魂が弱すぎる
大総統はまだ行方不明で
The Führer President is still missing?
下流で部下の死体が
Apparently, all they found was the corpse of one of his men downstream.
１つ見つかっただけだとさ
これで生きていたら奇跡ですね
It would be a miracle if he were to be alive after this.
I'll lead the search team, and I'll also ask the Northern army to lend us a hand.
北方軍にも協力してもらって
わしが捜索の指揮を執るから
You're going to step foot on the front lines yourself?
中将自らですか
彼奴の死体をこの目で見るまでは
I'll never be able to rest easy until I see his corpse with my own two eyes.
安心できんのだよ
You're not going to target Central as according to your original plan?
当初の予定どおり
セントラルを狙わないのですか
Nothing I can do.
しょうがないよ
I'll just have to hand over the fatty portions of Central to Colonel Mustang.
セントラルのおいしいところは
マスタング大佐にくれてやる
Currently, the Bradley administration is operating without any trouble.
現ブラッドレイ政権は
特に大きな問題もなく  機能している
If Colonel Mustang and Major General Armstrong were to go through with the operation,
マスタング大佐と
アームストロング少将のどちらも
このまま事を起こせば
謀反人扱いされるだろう
they'll probably be treated as rebels.
And when that happens, it'll be my turn to shine.
もしそうなったら
そのときこそがわしの出番だ
After they become seen as the villains,
あいつらに悪者になってもらってから
I, Lieutenant General Grumman, the defender of justice, will arrive on the scene.
正義の味方グラマン中将の登場とさせてもらう
In order for me to stand at the top of this country with the least amount of risk,
少ないリスクで
わしがこの国の実権を握るために
I'm going to need the younglings to pull the chestnuts out of the fire.
若い者に火中の栗を拾ってもらおうかのう
That's probably exactly what this raccoon is thinking right now.
とか考えているのだろうな
このタヌキは
I joined forces with him since we're right on the brink of the Promised Day,
約束の日を前に
手を組みはしたが
but I shouldn't let my guard down until the very end.
最後まで油断できんか…
A-Al...
ア…アル…
It's Pride.
プライドだ
プライド
'Pride'?
Yeah.
I guess he's sort of like our eldest brother.
オレたちの
いちばん上の兄ちゃんってとこか
A Homunculus?!
人造人間か
なんとしても裏切るのですね  グリード
So you're going to betray us no matter what, Greed?
Then at this point, you're nothing but an obstacle for us.
もはや君は我々にとって
邪魔者でしかない
Damn you...
くそが…
なんでここが分かった
How did you know we were here?!
てめぇ  アルに変装するなんて
How dare you transform into Al!
I didn't transform into anything.
変装ではありませんよ
This is really your little brother's body.
紛れもない  君の弟の体です
You son of a...!
野郎
I'm going to dispose of Greed right here and now.
グリードは
ここで始末させてもらいます
And then, I'm going to have the Fullmetal Alchemist come with me afterwards.
鋼の錬金術師は
一緒に来てもらいましょうか
Hey! You two should hide somewhere-
ゴリさんたちは逃げ…
って  早いな  お前ら
Wow, you guys sure didn't waste any time, did you?!
オレたちの野生の勘が
Our animal instincts are telling us not to fight that thing!
あれと戦うなといってる
お前は大丈夫なのか
Are you going to be okay?
大丈夫だよ  あいつら
Of course I am.
They can't kill Al and I because they need us for whatever reason.
オレとアルが必要だから殺せない
But on the other hand, I can give them everything I've got!
でもこっちは思いっ切り本気を出せる
I'm going to beat you to a pulp!
遠慮なく倒させてもらうぜ
You're right; I'm not going to kill you.
そうです  殺しはしません
However, I can't guarantee that you won't lose a limb or three.
手足の２３本は
ちぎれるかもしれませんが
おっと  スラムの方に
I can't escape into the slums!
逃げるわけにはいかねぇ
You can't guard against this guy!
こいつにガードなんて効かねぇぞ
危ねぇ
That was close!
Well, I've captured your friend.
さて  お友達も捕らえましたが  どうします
Do I also have to capture the people in the slums in order for you to cooperate with me?
スラムの人間も捕らえれば
言うことを聞きますか
He's good.
さすがだな
He's going right for your soft spots.
お前の嫌がるところを
真っ先に突いてくる
I can't be on the losing side all the time.
そう毎度やられっぱなしでは
いられねぇよな
なんだ
What?
停電
A power outage?
どうなってんだ
What's going on?!
I can't see anything,
何も見えんが  目玉も消えた
but the eyeballs have also disappeared.
Greed!
グリード
Is that you, Heinekel?
ハインケルか
What's going on?
なんだ  何がどうなった
What happened?!
A shadow only exists if there is light.
なに  光あっての影だ
真っ暗闇じゃ実体化もできねぇし
He can't even materialize in the dark,
オレたち同様 何も見えねぇってわけさ
and can't see anything just like us.
So he left?!
いなくなったのか
He's just lurking somewhere.
潜んでいるだけだ
If the lights come back on, he'll be back...
明かりがつけば  また現れる
おっと
What are we going to do, then?!
どうすんだよ
Heinekel... did you see Alphonse's shadow earlier?
ハインケル
さっきアルフォンスの影見たか
Yeah.
触手みたいなのがうねうねと
There were a lot of these tentacles crawling about.
そこじゃねぇ
Not that.
He was always near a large shadow, right?
必ず大きな影のそばにいたろ
Pride's real body is somewhere within the shadows of the forest.
本体は森の影の中にいる
His real body?!
本体
So it's not in Al's armor?!
鎧が本体じゃないのか
Nope.
違う  あいつ専用の
He has a container just for himself to use whenever he goes out.
お出かけ用の入れ物があるのさ
どんな入れ物だ
What kind of 'container'?
No moon or stars in the sky, huh...
月も星もなしですか
They can't maneuver in this darkness either.
この暗闇では
あちらも動けないはず
Guess I'll just have to wait for the slums to get their power back...
スラムの明かりが戻るのを待って…
逃がさん
You're not getting away!
この姿に動揺せず
So my child's figure doesn't stop you from attacking me.
攻撃してくるとはなかなか…
You're pretty good.
You're right. I do feel bad for having to kill a child!
確かにガキを手に掛けるのは
気が引けるがな
But then again,
それ以上に野生の勘が叫んでんだよ
my animal instincts are overwhelming my conscience!
It's telling me that I have to kill you here and now!
こいつは倒さなきゃやべぇってな
Ed!
エド
Hey, Ed!
ゴリさんか
Is that you, Donkey Kong?
How's your little brother doing?
弟は
He doesn't seem to have moved at all.
動いた様子はない
You can hear it when he does.
あいつ動いたら
ガシャガシャいうし
Okay. Let's leave this place for now.
よし  ひとまずここを離れよう
アルをほっとけっていうのか
You're telling me to abandon Al?!
I understand that you're worried,
心配なのは分かるが
下手に近づいて
but what if we were to approach him carelessly, just to find that it was a 	trap?
罠だったらどうする
We need to stick together until Heinekel takes care of Pride in order to avoid accidentally attacking each 	other.
ハインケルがプライドをどうにかするまで
同士討ちを避けるためにも
一緒にいるんだ
Is that... the sound of Lion King fighting?
あの音
ライオンのおっさんが戦ってんのか
Let's just leave it to the nocturnals for now.
暗闇は夜行性動物に
任せとけって話よ
Damn that Pride...
プライドめ…なぜ
How did he know we were here?
オレたちの居場所が分かった
That shouldn't be a part of his abilities...
あいつにそんな能力は…
伏せろ
Duck!
Smells like the Fullmetal Alchemist.
鋼の錬金術師のにおい
Smells like Greed.
グリードのにおい
この声はグラトニー
Judging from the voice... Gluttony?!
Him?!
あいつか
Now I get it.
なるほど
グラトニーの嗅覚を使って
He used Gluttony's keen sense of smell to find us.
オレたちを捜し当てたってわけか
I also smell a scent of a guy I don't recognize!
あと  知らないヤツのにおいは
I can eat him, right?
食べていいよね
ご指名だ  ダリウス
He's talking about you, Darius.
That one's also a Homunculus.
あいつも人造人間だぜ
あんな化け物クラスとどうやって…
How do you expect me to fight against a monster like that?
あいつは
He's just following his nose.
においを頼りに動いているだけだ
In this situation, you should be evenly matched.
今なら  五分五分で
戦えるんじゃないのか
My animal instincts are telling me not to do it, but...
野生の勘がやめとけって
いってるんだけどなぁ…
Men are all about guts!
男は度胸だ  先手必勝
Victory goes to the swiftest!
One more!
もう一発
Damn it, Donkey Kong...
ひでぇよ  ゴリさん…
I thought we were sticking together to avoid attacking each other...
同士討ちを避けるために
一緒にいたんじゃあ…
すまん
My bad.
I guess Gluttony will still have the advantage in the dark.
やはり  暗闇では
グラトニーの有利は動かんか
だが明かりをつければ  プライドが…
But if we were to turn on the lights, Pride would...
This is troublesome.
厄介なこった
Hey, Greed.
グリード
That you, Lin?
リンか
Switch with me for a sec.
交代しろ  オレなら
I can sense the aura of the Homunculi.
人造人間の気配を察知できる
I was also the one to notice Pride, right?
プライドに気づいたのもオレだったろう
I can fight better than you in this darkness.
この暗闇なら
オレの方がうまく立ち回れる
Guess I don't have a choice!
しょうがねぇ
この体持ち逃げすんなよ
You better not run off with this body!
Cut the jokes!
ふざけんな  もともとオレの体だ
It's my body to begin with!
Rub a dub dub, thanks for the-
いただきま…
そこだ
There you are!
Nice one!
いいねぇ
お前と組んでよかったぜ
I'm glad I picked you, man!
どうも
I'm honored!
Is it Lin now?!
リンか
Yeah!
You're making me angry...!
おで怒った  おなかすいた
And I'm also hungry!
なのに  お前ら
But you guys aren't letting me eat you!
さっさと食われてくれない
That's why...
だから  丸ごと飲んでやる
...I'm just going to swallow you!
I have a bad feeling!
やばい感じだ
やばいって  何が
What do you mean?!
Something's coming.
何か来る
What , exactly?!
何かって  何
This is... just like back then!
これはあのときの
ちょちょっ  ちょっ  ちょっと
Hey... Whoa, whoa!
What do you guys see that I don't?!
お前ら  何見えてんの
ノーマルのオレに説明しろ
I'm just a normal guy! Explain it to me!
何っ
あで
What was that?!
なんだ
Stay still!
じっとしてろ
Is there someone else?!
まだ何かいるのか
I have no idea.
分からん
分からんが…これは
I haven't got a clue, but this is...!
I...
この…におい…
I know this smell...!
おで…知ってる…
Glad to see you're in top shape!
息災で何より
I've been waiting for you, Lan Fan!
待っていたぞ  ランファン
The promise we never made
交わしたはずのない約束が
Kawashita hazu no nai yakasoku ga
yet again
今日も
Kyou mo
tries to snatch our future away from us.
僕らの未来を奪おうとする
Bokura no mirai wo ubaou to suru
Why is it that we can't rejoice
欲しがっていたものを手にしても
Hoshigatteita mono wo te ni shitemo
straight from the heart
素直に
Sunao ni
when we obtain something we've always been after?
うまく笑えないのはなぜだろう
Umaku waraenai nowa nazedarou
The overflowing tears aren't from feebleness or remorse.
あふれる涙は　弱さや後悔じゃない
Afureru namida wo yowasa ya koukai ja nai
They're fragments born from agony.
イタミが生んだカケラで
Itami ga unda kakera de
Of all the moments and destinies,
どんな瞬間だって運命だって
Donna shunkan datte unmei datte
I realized there's one absolute certainty.
ひとつだけ確かなものがあると知った
Hitotsu dake tashika na mono ga aru to shitta
Even if things get tough and I'm at my limit
限界だって困難だって
Genkai datte konnan datte
I refuse to give up.
あきらめたくないよ
Akirametakunaiyo
Please, don't let go.
このまま離さないで
Konomama hanasanaide
I can feel the warmth of your right hand
かたく握りしめた　君の右手のぬくもり
Kataku nigirishimeta kimi no migite no nukumori
where it's tightly joined with my left.
ここにあるから
Koko ni arukara
日本語字幕仕上げ：XIAOBIN
敵を知り  己を知って
If you only feel fear after knowing both the abilities of your enemy and yourself,
得るものが恐怖なら
しっぽを巻いて逃げるがいい
flee with your tail between your legs.
漫遊字幕組
http://popgo.net/bbs
踏みとどまり
However, if you're going to stand firm and fight with a focused mind,
知恵を絞って戦うのなら
必ず  勝機は見いだせる
you will definitely have victory within reach.
次回　鋼の錬金術師
Next time, Fullmetal Alchemist:
Fullmetal  Alchemist
第４８話　『地下道の誓い』
Episode 48, The Oath in the Tunnel.
仲間の血をもって勝利するは
Is it right or wrong to achieve victory by sacrificing a fellow comrade?
是か否か